{
  "sourceFile": "2019-2020-International-Geography-Bee-Regional-Quiz-Tournament-Round-1.txt",
  "count": 10,
  "items": [
    {
      "qno": 1,
      "question": "This peninsula is home to the incomplete Diamond Tower, which will be the first building to twist 360 degrees. Another under construction tower on this peninsula is a 3,300 foot neo-futurist project designed by Adrian Smith. This peninsula is also home the world’s tallest building, Burj Khalifa. For ten points, name this peninsula whose skyscrapers are centered in cities such as Jeddah, Dubai, and Mecca.",
      "answer": "Arabian Peninsula"
    },
    {
      "qno": 2,
      "question": "One of these systems in Glasgow consists of two concentric circles and is operated by the Strathclyde Partnership. One of these systems found in Paris has several cast iron entrances designed by Hector Guimard. Portions of one of these systems in London include Euston and Paddington. For ten points, name these systems of trains that run underground, which are often called rapid transit systems.",
      "answer": "subway systems [or metro systems"
    },
    {
      "qno": 3,
      "question": "The village of Zermatt is overlooked by this mountain and is the base for most climbs of this mountain. This mountains first ascent included Lord Francis Douglas and ended with four of the seven climbers deaths. This nearly pyramidal mountain lies in the canton of Valais. For ten points, name this last major mountain in the Alps to be climbed, which sits on the Swiss-Italian border.",
      "answer": "Matterhorn"
    },
    {
      "qno": 4,
      "question": "The first one of these locations was founded by C.E. Borchgrevink on Ridley Beach. The southernmost Chinese operated one of these locations is known as Kunlun. The largest one of these places is named for being located on McMurdo Sound. One of these locations named for Amundsen-Scott is located at the south pole. For ten points, name these scientific facilities located on the southernmost continent.",
      "answer": "Research stations in Antarctica"
    },
    {
      "qno": 5,
      "question": "This mountain was formerly home to the Drygalski Glacier. This mountain’s current glaciers include the Furtwangler and Rebmann glaciers. This mountain’s peaks of Mawenzi and Kibo are separated by the Saddle Plateau. This mountain is known as Uharu in the Swahili language. For ten points, name this extinct stratovolcano in Tanzania, the tallest mountain in Africa.",
      "answer": "Mount Kilimanjaro"
    },
    {
      "qno": 6,
      "question": "The British Overseas Territories of Akrotiri and Dhekelia are located on this island. This island is divided by the Green Line, with its northern half being an unrecognized independent country. This island is home to the Kyrenia and Troodos mountains. This island is shared by Turkish and Greek inhabitants and has its capital at Nicosia. For ten points, name this large Mediterranean island found south of Turkey.",
      "answer": "Cyprus Page 1 IGB Regionals 2019-2020 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "qno": 7,
      "question": "The only non-American alligator species in the world is endemic to this river, which also names a species of finless porpoise. This river was formerly home to the baiji river dolphin, which was harmed by the construction of the Three Gorges Dam. This river flows into the East China Sea near Shanghai. For ten points, name this Chinese river, the longest river in Asia.",
      "answer": "Yangtze River"
    },
    {
      "qno": 8,
      "question": "This location is home to a set of multicolored springs called the Artist’s Paintpots which are located in the Gibbon Geyser Basin. The Morning Glory Pool, a yellow and blue spring, is located in this park. This park is home to a geyser named due to erupting at regular intervals. Old Faithful is located in, for ten points, what National Park found mostly in Wyoming, the oldest in the United States?",
      "answer": "Yellowstone National Park"
    },
    {
      "qno": 9,
      "question": "The mouth of the Catatumbo River in this country is home to a perpetual lightning storm. That river empties into this country’s lake Maracaibo. This country is also home to where the Orinoco River empties into the Caribbean Sea. This country is home to the highest uninterrupted waterfall in the world, Angel Falls. For ten points, name this South American country east of Colombia with capital Caracas.",
      "answer": "Venezuela"
    },
    {
      "qno": 10,
      "question": "Lago Alajuela’s flooding caused the closure of this structure. This structure was created following the Hay-Bunau-Varilla Treaty. This structure is crossed by the Bridge of the Americas. This structure Gatun Lake and the Gaillard Cut lie along this structure. For ten points, name this structure that connects the Caribbean Sea to the Pacific Ocean, a waterway through its namesake Central American country.",
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    }
  ]
}